Sillitoe mss. II, 1950-1996 LMC 2141
Lilly Library
Sillitoe mss. II
1950-1996
Lilly Library
Sillitoe, Alan
LMC 2141
28 Boxes 27 standard, 1 custom
The Sillitoe mss. II, 1950-1996, consists of the papers of writer Alan Sillitoe, 1928-2010.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired: 1998
Biographical Note
Alan Sillitoe, 1928-2010, was born in Nottingham, England, the son of a tannery laborer. He left school at 14 to work in a bicycle plant, and later joined the Royal Air Force. He served as a radio operator from 1946-1949 in Malaya, and, upon leaving the service, was found to have tuberculosis confining him to bed for many months. A blessing in disguise, Sillitoe received a small disability pension and so was able to pursue his dream of learning to write. His first novel Saturday Night and Sunday Morning was proclaimed by some critics as the finest novel of 1958. The Loneliness of the Long–Distance Runner (contained in a short story collection of the same name) firmly established his literary reputation the following year. Both have been translated into numerous languages, made into films, and performed on stage and on television. Sillitoe wrote and published a number of other novels, in addition to magazine and newspaper articles, poetry and many short stories.
Scope and Contents
The Sillitoe mss. II, 1950-1996, consists of the papers of writer Alan Sillitoe, 1928-2010. The correspondence is mostly with colleagues and friends, including: Yehudi Amichai, Leonard Baskin, John Bratby, H.M. (Hillel Matthew) Daleski, Robert Graves, Polly Hope, Glyn Hughes, Ted Hughes, Christopher Logue, Aharon Megged, John Sawkins, Josef Śkvorecký, and Benjamin Tammuz. The writings contain drafts and manuscripts of articles, novels, poems, scripts, short stories, speeches and translations, both published and unpublished, including manuscripts for The Loneliness of the Long Distance Runner and Saturday Night and Sunday Morning. Miscellaneous items include: financial papers and hundreds of clippings.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; and, III. Miscellaneous.
Related Materials
See Sillitoe mss. and Sillitoe mss. III, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana
Authors, English--Correspondence; Literature--translating; Amichai, Yehuda, 1924-2000; Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000.; Bratby, John, 1928-1992.; Daleski, H. M. (Hillel Matthew), 1926- .; Graves, Robert, 1895-1985.; Hughes, Glyn, 1935- .; Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998.; Logue, Christopher, 1926- .; Megged, Aharon, 1920- .; Sawkins, John.; Škvorecký, Josef.; Sillitoe, Alan.; Tammuz, Benjamin, 1919-1989.; Sillitoe, Alan --Correspondence.
- I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  Arrangement
  Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Also included are some drafts and carbons of Sillitoe's letters which are filed with the correspondent.
  List of correspondents:
  A.P. Watt & Son
  Abelman, Paul
  Adkin, Gilbert
  Adkin, Mary
  Amichai, Yehudi
  Amichai, Hannah
  Amis, Martin
  Anders Nyborg A/S International Forlag
  Anderson, Lindsay, 1923-
  Archer, L.A.C.
  Ashenden, Robin
  Atkin, Pete
  Atwood, Margaret (dictated, not signed)
  Baerlocher, N
  Bailey, C.F.
  Bar-Adon, Pessah, 1907-
  Barnett, Bill
  Barnett, Steven
  Bartelot, R.G.
  Bartov, Hanoch
  Baskin, Leonard, 1922-
  Becker, Harold
  Belbin, David
  Bell, Alan
  Bell, Veveen
  Berheta, Margaret
  Berman, Ed
  Bernard, Suzanne
  Bidwell, Ginger
  Birmingham City Council, Birmingham Libraries
  The Black Dwarf
  Blomberg, Charles
  Böll, Heinrich, 1917-
  Books and Bookmen
  Boré, Katia
  Bowles, Paul
  Boyson, Rhodes
  Braine, John
  Bratby, John, 1928-
  Braun, Armand
  and Marina Lupas
  British Broadcasting Corporation
  The British Council
  British Rail International
  Brocard
  Brownjohn, Alan, 1931-
  The Bulgarian News Agency
  Carpenter, Humphrey
  Cecil, David, Lord, 1902-
  Charles Scribner's Sons
  Chatto & Windus
  Chernin, Kim
  Children and Youth Aliyah
  Clemens, Cyril, 1902-
  Colin, Rosica (see: Rosica Colin Ltd.)
  Collay, Sophie
  Combes, Francis
  Comstock and Rose, Attorneys and Counselors at Law
  Constable Publishers
  Contemporary Jewish Library
  Coover, Robert
  Cordell, Frank
  Craigie, John
  Crawford, Max, 1938-
  Croft, Andy
  Cutler, Ivor
  Cutting, Nigel
  Daily Telegram
  Daleski, H.M. (Hillel Matthew)
  Daleski, Shirley
  de Cacqueray, Elizabeth
  de Laneroll, Ros
  Delaney, Shelagh, 1939-
  Delenclos Déborah
  Dillon, Millicent G.
  Diogenes Verlag
  Douthwaite, Pat (Hogarth)
  Dove, Rita and Fred Viebahn, 1947-
  Dragadze, Tamara
  Duffy, Peter and Antonia
  Edwards, Anne, 1927-
  Evnine, George
  Fainlight, Harry, d.1982 (b.1935)
  Farmer, Penelope, 1939-
  Feinstein, Elaine
  Ferlinghetti, Lawrence (see: Perret, Christopher)
  Fink, Ida
  Finney, Albert, 1939-
  Florence, Peter
  Foster John L. (John Lawrence), 1930-
  Frean, Peter
  Friedlander, Albert H.
  Friedlander, Daniel
  Frischknecht, H
  Furtseva, Ekaterina
  Fussell, Paul, 1924- and Harriette
  Galaif, Lisa
  Gardner, Joan
  Gardner, John
  Garfinkel, Sharon
  Garnett, David, 1892-
  Geraghty, Tony
  Gilbert, Martin, 1936-
  Godwin, Fay
  Gough, Dilys
  Grafton Books
  Graham, W.S. (William Sydney), 1918-
  Graves, Beryl
  Graves, Robert, 1895-
  Graves, Thomas
  Greene, Graham, 1904-
  The Guardian
  Halban, Peter
  Halperin, John, 1941-
  Halter, Aloma
  Hanawa, Katsuichi
  Hardman, Leslie H.
  Hardy, Barbara Nathan
  Harjula, Terry
  Harper Collins Publishers
  Hartshorne, Sally A.
  Heitler, Emmett H.
  Heponstall, Rayner
  Hill, Susan
  Hodgast, Matthew
  Hodgson, Barbara
  Hoffman, Daniel
  Hoffman, Eve
  Holland, Roy
  Hope, Polly
  Horovitz, Michael, 1935-
  Hospital, Janette Turner, 1942-
  Hughes, Glyn, 1935-
  Hughes, Jane
  Hughes, Roya
  Hughes, Olwyn
  Hughes, Ted, 1930-
  Huisman-Berera, Anita
  Hurst, George
  Hutchison, Sidney C.
  Hyatt, Mark
  Hynes, Samuel Lynn
  Imperial War Museum
  Isherwood, Christopher, 1904-
  Jay, Peter, 1945-
  Jeantet, Laura
  Jepson, Selwyn, 1899-
  Jerusalem Post
  Jewish Chronicle
  Johnson, B.S. (Bryan Stanley, 1933-1973
  Johnson, Robert Thomas
  Joseph, Jenny
  Joubert, Jean, 1928-
  Joubert, Denyse
  Karl, Frederick Robert, 1927-
  Kazantzis, Judith
  Keevil McIntosh Gibson Limited
  Kennedy, William, 1928-
  Kermode, Frank, 1919-
  Kéry, László
  Kirkham, Pat
  Knowles, Mike
  Kollek, Teddy, 1911-
  Kushner, Tony
  Kustow, Michael
  Laurence, Margaret
  Le Fanu, Mark
  Lehnig, Hans-Joachim
  Lesser, Wendy
  Lessing, Doris May, 1919-
  Levi, Peter
  Levy, John D.A.
  Linscott, Gill
  Little, Brown and Company Publishers
  Logue, Christopher, 1926-
  London, Vivian
  Long, Gerry
  Luttrell, Steve
  McAteer, Tracey T.
  McCourt, Kevin C.
  Macedo, Helder
  McGrath, Pat
  Macmillan & Co. Ltd.
  Manchester Polytechnic
  Marmur, Dow
  Marris, Robin Lapthorn, 1924-
  Martin, Helen
  Martin, Phillip
  Martin, William
  Mason, Stanley
  Mattea, Giovanna
  Matthews, Stephen M.
  Maynard, Edward J.
  Megged, Aharon, 1920-
  Mercer, David, 1928-1980
  Miyake, Okiko
  Mockridge, Clara
  Monsees, Robert A.
  Moscow Literary Gazette (Prudkov)
  Murdoch, Iris
  National Book League
  Nautical Magazine
  New Left Review (incomplete letter)
  The New Yorker
  Newton, Roy
  Nottingham High School
  Nottinghamshire Constabulary
  Nottinghamshire County Council
  Observer
  Orbis, an International Quarterly of Poetry and Prose
  Osborne, John
  Owen, David
  Oz, Amos
  Pan Books Ltd.
  Patterson, Christina
  Perlès, Alfred
  Perret, Christopher
  Perutz, Kathrin, 1939-
  Peter Owen Ltd. Publishers
  Peters, Catherine
  Pinchevsky, Mark
  Pinter, Harold, 1930-
  The Poetry Society
  Polkey, Dennis
  Prant, Carolyn & Peter
  Price, Robert
  Price-Jones, David
  Priestley, Jacquetta Hopkins, 1910-
  Puig, Valentí
  Raphael, Frederic, 1931-
  Ray, Cyril, 1908-
  Reisz, Karel
  Rekunkov, A.M. (Aleksandr Mikhaílovich)
  Reynolds, Mack
  Richardson, Richard
  Richardson, Tony, 1928-1991
  Rikman, Tamara
  Riley, Jonathan
  Robinson, Joan R.
  Robson Books Ltd.
  Rosenblum, E.S.
  Rosica Colin Ltd.
  Ross, Tony
  Royle, Nicholas
  Ruben, Simon Daniel
  Rubens, Bernice
  Sawkins, John
  Schade, Frauke
  Schlachter, Ann
  Schlachter, Ronald
  Schulman, Grace
  Scott, Michael
  Sergeant, Howard, 1914-
  Shamir, Moshe, 1921-
  Shinada, Shohei
  Silk, Dennis, 1928-
  Sillitoe, Brian
  Sillitoe, Michael
  Simon & Schuster
  Sinclair, Clive, 1948-
  Sindal, Bernard
  Škvorecký, Josef
  Snow, C.P. (Charles Percy), 1905-
  Spector, David
  Spender, Stephen, 1909-
  Steadman, Ralph
  Steen, Larry
  Steiner, George
  Steven, Stewart, 1937-
  Stevenson, Anne
  and Peter Lucas
  Stoppard, Tom
  The Suffolk Book League
  Summers, John
  Sunday Times
  Surel, Jacques
  Szirtes, George, 1948-
  Tabata, Nobuko
  Tammuz, Benjamin, 1919-
  Tarr, John Charles
  Tarrant, Crea
  Tessa Sayle Literary and Dramatic Agency
  The Times
  Tuck, Anthony
  Tynan, Kenneth, 1927-
  Ungerer, Tomi, 1931-
  Upchurch, Clarissa (see Szirtes, George)
  Vansittart, Peter
  W.H. Allen & Co. Ltd.
  Wanamaker, Sam, 1919-
  Waugh, Alec, 1898-
  Weil, James L.
  Wesker, Arnold, 1932-
  Whine, Mike
  White, Patrick
  Willcox, Joan
  Willis, Ted
  Wilson, Angus
  Wilson, Colin, 1931-
  Wilson, Jean Moorcroft (see: Woolf, Cecil)
  Wolsen, Sonya
  Women's Campaign for Soviet Jewry
  Woolf, Cecil
  The Writer and Human Rights in Aid of Amnesty International
  Yehoshua, A.B.
  Yoken, Mel B.
  - A-S (Box 1)
  - T - Z; unidentified (Box 2)
- II. Writings (Box 2)
  The writings are arranged in the following subseries: MAJOR WORKS, such as novels, travel books and published plays; ARTICLES AND SHORT STORIES; BOOK REVIEWS; INTRODUCTIONS; POETRY; SCRIPTS, including film, stage and television plays; SPEECHES; TRANSLATIONS; WRITINGS BY OTHERS
  - MAJOR WORKS (Box 2)
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    Includes both published and unpublished works.
    - Alan Sillitoe: Life Without Armour (Box 2)
      - folder 7: Bound notebook, revised, with some wireless notes. ca. 136 pages (Box 2)
      - folder 8: Notebook, first autograph draft of notes, autograph and typed, 100 pages with ca. 20 pages of insertions (Box 2)
      - folder 9: Notebook containing 27 pages of autograph manuscript towards the first draft (Box 2)
      - folder 10: Autograph manuscript in a notebook, 174 pages (Box 2)
      - folder 11: Autograph manuscript in a notebook, [261] pages (Box 2)
      - folders 12-17: Disorganized drafts, revised typescripts (Box 2)
      - folder 18: Penultimate draft. Typescript, with corrections (Box 2)
      - folder 1: Penultimate draft... (Box 3)
      - folder 2: Computer printouts for The Daily Mail of a series based on the book (Box 3)
    - The Bandstand (Box 3)
      - folder 3: Typescript of an unpublished novel with few revisions, 181 pages. (Box 3)
        General
        This work was commissioned as a film script by Ulla Jacobson, the Swedish film star, and was taken up by Constantine Films of Stutgart for £250, but was never made. It was written in Soller in 1956/7.
        Also includes: Autograph and typescript notes on a motor trip on Majorca, on the versos of final pages of draft, with a sketch map and a page of a poem by Ruth Fainlight.
    - By What Road (Box 3)
      - folder 4: Unpublished manuscript, autograph with revisions, 295 pages. (Box 3)
        Sillitoe's first novel, written in Nottingham and dated Oct. 24, 1950. Sillitoe attributes the survival of this manuscript to the fact that he exchanged it with his brother for a suit. He bought it back in 1960 with £50 of the proceeds from Saturday Night and Sunday Morning.
    - Collected Stories (Box 3)
      - folder 5: Typescript of Preface (Box 3)
    - Death of William Posters (Box 3)
      - folder 6: Notebook, autograph manuscript with revisions, Vol. I, 94 leaves, with 20 typed pages with autograph revisions, loosely inserted, May 8, 1961 (Box 3)
      - folder 7: Notebook, autograph manuscript with revisions, Vol. II, leaves numbered 95-172, 18 pages of autograph manuscript loosely inserted (Box 3)
      - folder 8: Notebook, autograph manuscript with revisions, Vol. III, leaves numbered 174-241, datedplus 43 pages of household accounts of, 16 December 1963; 1961-2 (Box 3)
      - folder 9: Notebook, autograph manuscript with revisions, Vol. IV, leaves numbered to 242-323, datedplus autograph draft of a poem Tree, July 20, 1964 (Box 3)
      - folder 10-11: The second draft, revised typescript, ca. 350 pages (Box 3)
      - folder 12-14: Third Draft. Typescript with some autograph revisionsca.400 pages, May 31-Nov. 24, 1961 (Box 3)
    - The Deserters (Box 3)
      - folder 15: Revised typescript of an unpublished novel, with a page of autograph character notes, 401 pages, bound. (Box 3)
        Written between 1950 and 1953 in Majorca.
        Includes the following on the versos: (1) Mr. Allen's Island, fantasy novel, 86 pages; (2) Once in the weekend, autograph with revisions. Became the first chapter of Saturday Night and Sunday Morning, 10 pages, dated 8 Feb 1954; (3) Autograph list of stories on the same theme, with notes of where they were eventually used, including Saturday Night and Sunday Morning; (4) Autograph note on Majorca, comprising two paragraphs of an unfinished story: plus 4 lines later incorporated into Key to the Door (chapter 5); (5) Autograph note on travel from Granada to Malaga 1.5 pages [Sept. 1953]; (6) Autograph notes, with a few revisions, on Letters from Malaya [see Key to the Door], 30 pages; (7) Autograph notes on the scenery of Soller; (8) Chopin's Winter in Majorca, by Luis Ripoli, autograph notes on a translation by Sillitoe, published in 1955 with an introduction by Robert Graves, 4 pages; (9) Autograph notes of characters and chapters for Saturday Night and Sunday Morning, 4 pages; (10) Saturday Night and Sunday Morning. Autograph, with light revision, of Chapters 6 to 18 (the end in this version), First draft 1955-6, 181 pages, and 3 pages of chapter headings and notes. To lighten the load of luggage, Sillitoe at that time was not in the habit of keeping manuscripts. Chapters 6-18 were preserved because they were bound in this volume along with unpublished material; (11) Miscellaneous notes about writing, on Scott FitzGerald's The Beautiful and The Damned, The Rates, and What will be the plot of my novel, 8 pages; (12) On Saturday Afternoon, autograph, 3 pages, late 1957. This story was published in The Loneliness of the Long-distance Runner; (13) Key to the Door, autograph manuscript of the first chapter, with light corrections, 12 pages; (14) The Loneliness of the Long-distance Runner, autograph chapter for the continuation, with light revision and a list of chapter headings for the continuation, 19 pages. This chapter was not used. It was written in Camden Town in the Summer of 1958; (15) Autograph notes on writing travel books; (16) Autograph story about a kitten, Oct. 21, 1955, 2 pages; (17) Baedeker to Damascony, autograph notes for a novel. This was eventually used for Travels in Nihilon (1971); (18) Autograph note about feeding a kitten from the back door in Majorca, Oct. 1, 1955.
    - Diary to Israel and Back (Box 3)
      - folder 16-17: Corrected typescript (Box 3)
    - Down from the Hill (Box 4)
      - folder 1: Autograph manuscript, July 11, 1983, 61 pages (Box 4)
      - folder 2: Typescript, revised, ca.200 pages (Box 4)
      - folder 3: Third/fourth draft, typescript, revised, 185 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 4-5: Fourth/fifth draft, typescript, revised, 251 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 6-7: Top copy, 258 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 8-9: Second copy, 258 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 10-11: Printer's copy (Box 4)
    - Every Day of the Week (Box 4)
      - folder 12: Autograph copy of contents (Box 4)
    - Flame of Life (Original title: The Real Thing) (Box 4)
      - folders 13-14: Three notebooks, autograph manuscript begunfinished 222 pages, Aug. 16, 1967; Apr. 23, 1973 (Box 4)
      - folder 15: Revised autograph and typescript pages, ca.100 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 16-18: Second draft, revised typescript, 554 pages (Box 4)
      - folders 1-2: Third draft, revised typescript, 484 pages (Box 5)
      - folders 3-5: Fourth and final draft, second carbon, 378 pages (Box 5)
      - folder 6: Uncorrected page proofs (Box 5)
    - Guzman Go Home and Other Stories (Box 5)
      - folders 7-13: Autograph and typescript drafts of the following short stories: Canals; Chicken; Guzman, Go Home; Isaac Starbuck; Revenge; The Road; The Rope Trick (Box 5)
      - folder 14: Draft of Preface; paperback cover; advertisement (Box 5)
      - folder 15: Printer's typescript (Box 5)
    - Her Victory (Box 5)
      - folders 16-20: Four notebooks, autograph manuscript, 410 pages, plus loose leaves, finished, 24 June 1980 (Box 5)
      - folder 1: Pre-first draft writings, ca.120 pages (Box 6)
      - folders 2-7: First draft, revised typescript, 754 pages, plus pages for insertion and rewrites (Box 6)
      - folders 8-10: Third draft, typescript, 738 pages (Box 6)
      - folders 11-12: Third draft,... (Box 6)
      - folders 13-15: Rewrites, typescript and autograph, ca.300 pages (Box 6)
      - folder 16: Printer's copy, largely unrevised, 781 pages (Box 6)
      - folders 1-3: Printer's copy,... (Box 6)
    - Key to the Door (Box 6)
      - folders 4-5: Revised typescript, 1954-1956, 311 pages. (Box 6)
        This is the earliest version of Key to the Door, previously called Letters from Malaya. The first draft was lost.
      - folder 6: Initial autograph notes, with revisions 2 pages; and typescript of early version, 2 pages, Soller, [1953]; 1953 (Box 6)
      - folder 7: Notebook, autograph manuscript beginning with Chapter 18 and with an autograph plan for the novel on the front paste down, pagination runs from 390-570. (Box 6)
        At the end is a first draft of The Firebug.
      - folder 8: Notebook and some loose leaves, autograph, pages 571-697, Tangiers, Dec. 12, 1960 (Box 6)
      - folders 9-13: Revised typescript and autograph pages, ca.400 pages (Box 6)
      - folders 14-15: Printer's copy, with a few autograph revisions, 486 pages; paperback cover (Box 6)
    - Last Loves (Box 8)
      - folders 1-3: Three autograph notebooks, ca.200 pages (Box 8)
      - folders 4-5: Second draft, revised typescript, [255] pages (Box 8)
      - folders 6-7: Third draft, revised typescript, 243 pages, plus 50 pages of notes and additions (Box 8)
      - folders 8-11: Fourth draft, unrevised, 2 copies; book jacket and copies of advertisements (Box 8)
    - Leonard's War (Box 8)
      - folder 12: Autograph notebook, 98 numbered pages. (Box 8)
        Contains 14 pages of notes on the robbing of their car which became an article in The Guardian
      - folders 13-15: Second draft, revised typescript, ca.400 pages (Box 8)
      - folders 16-17: Third draft, revised typescript, 300 pages (Box 8)
      - folders 1-2: Fourth draft, revised typescript, 264 pages (Box 9)
      - folders 3-4: Fifth draft, revised typescript, 303 pages (Box 9)
    - Life Goes On (Box 9)
      - folder 5-6: Two autograph notebooks323 pages, 1972-1979 (Box 9)
      - folder 7: Revised typescript pages removed from above notebook, 59 pages (Box 9)
      - folders 8-11: Second draft, revised typescript, 610 pages (Box 9)
      - folders 12-16: Third draft, revised typescript, 713 pages, plus ca. 50 miscellaneous pages (Box 9)
      - folder 1: Third draft,... (Box 10)
      - folders 2-5: Final uncorrected typescript version (Box 10)
      - folders 6: Revised autograph and typescript pages. 16 pages (Box 10)
      - folders 7-9: Printer's copy (Box 10)
      - folder 10-11: Proofread copy (Box 10)
      - folder 12: Uncorrected proof of book (Box 10)
    - The Loneliness of a Long-distance Runner (novella) (Box 10)
      - folder 13: Typescript and autograph draft pages and notes (Box 10)
      - folder 14-15: Autograph and typescript notes and pages concerning continuation of LDR as a novel, with revisions, written at Camden Town in 1958, ca. 200 pages (Box 10)
      - folder 16: Proof for paperback cover; poster in German; related photocopy of article (Box 10)
    - The Loneliness of a Long-distance Runner (short stories) (Box 10)
      - folder 17: Revised typescript, 228 pages (Box 10)
      - folder 18: Revised notes for The Fishing Boat Picture 6 pages (Box 10)
      - folder 19: Autograph list of the short stories in LDR, 1 page; proofs for paperback covers (Box 10)
      - folder 20: Photocopy of typescript of book adapted for Bullseye by Jean Nobes 103 pages (Box 10)
    - The Lost Flying Boat (Box 10)
      - folders 21-22: Autograph manuscript, 206 pages, loose and notebook, Dec. 1, 1981-July 24, 1982 (Box 10)
      - folders 1-3: Second draft, revised typescript, ca. 550 pages (Box 11)
      - folders 4-7: Third draft, revised typescript, ca. 500 pages (Box 11)
      - folders 8-9: Penultimate draft, with some revisions, 383 pages (Box 11)
      - folders 10-11: Final draft of third copy, 338 pages (Box 11)
      - folder 12: Autograph notes, 20 pages (Box 11)
      - folders 13-14: Printer's copy, 338 pages (Box 11)
      - folder 15: Photographs and postcards of flying boats and two examples of the paperback covers; advertisement (Box 11)
    - The Man Without a Home (Box 11)
      - folder 16: Typescript of an unpublished novel with very few revisions, 274 pages. No other version or copy survives. It was written in Menton and Soller in, 1952-1953 (Box 11)
    - Men, Women and Children (Box 11)
      - folder 17: Drafts of Table of Contents and Foreword (Box 11)
      - folders 18: Autograph and typescript drafts of the following short story: Before Snow Comes (Box 11)
      - folder 1-8: Autograph and typescript drafts of the following short stories: The Chiker; The End of Enoch?; Enoch's Two Letters; Mimic; Pit Strike; Scenes from the Life of Margaret; A Trip to Southwell; The View (Box 12)
      - folders 9-10: Printer's copy, 195 pages, including paperback cover (Box 12)
    - Mountains and Caverns (Box 12)
      - folder 11: Drafts of introductions and acknowledgements (Box 12)
      - folders 12-26: Autograph and typescript drafts of the following essays: Arnold Bennett: The Man From the North; 'Che' Guevara; Destiny of Insignificance; Evacuated; Government Forms; Lawrence and District; The Long Piece; Maps; Mountains and Caverns; National Service; Poor People; Robert Tressell; Sport and Nationalism; Through the Tunnel; The Wild Horse (Box 12)
      - folder 27: Typescript of third copy (Box 12)
    - Mr. Allen's Island (Box 12)
      - folder 28: Revised typescript of an unpublished fantasy novel, sketch map, 217 pages, Dec. 20, 1954 (Box 12)
        (see also: Box 3, folder 15, no. 1)
    - The Open Door (Box 12)
      - folders 29-31: Three notebooks, autograph manuscript, 270 pages, with ca. 15 pages loosely inserted. (Box 12)
        At the end of vol.3 is a manuscript of a lecture (7 pages), additions to the novel (16 pages), the preface to Collected Stories (4 pages), and My Country Childhood (4 pages)
      - folders 1-4: Second draft, revised typescript, 639 pages (Box 13)
      - folders 5-9: Draft (fourth?), revised typescript, 800 pages (Box 13)
      - folders 10-13: Penultimate draft, revised typescript, 549 pages (Box 13)
      - folder 14: Miscellaneous draft pages, revised typescript, ca.900 pages (Box 13)
      - folders 1-4: Miscellaneous draft pages,... (Box 14)
      - folder 5: Book jacket; paperback cover (Box 14)
    - Out of the Whirlpool (Box 14)